<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><updated>2018-09-16T17:12:11+12:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Matthew Jeffery</title><subtitle>Student • Web Developer</subtitle><entry><title type="html">WordPress Page Load Times</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/28/wordpress_load_times/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WordPress Page Load Times"/><published>2018-08-28T04:15:05+12:00</published><updated>2018-08-28T04:15:05+12:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/08/28/wordpress_load_times</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/28/wordpress_load_times/">&lt;p&gt;Thanks to those of you who gave me feedback on my post, “Should I use WordPress or build my own website?”.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I really appreciated your feedback and would like to use this post to discuss one of the comments I received: “Use WordPress as your CMS in a headless manner which will let you cache pages for future visitors”. This was a great idea and after doing some research of my own, I came up with a condensed list of the primary reasons why your WordPress website might have slow loading times.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h5 id=&quot;wordpress-configuration&quot;&gt;WordPress Configuration&lt;/h5&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ensure your website is properly configured by using cached pages. If your server isn’t using cached pages, it will overload your server, thus causing your website to run slowly and potentially crash.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h5 id=&quot;bad-plugins&quot;&gt;Bad Plugins&lt;/h5&gt; &lt;p&gt;If you are using poorly developed or outdated plugins, you may find your website is drastically slowed down.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h5 id=&quot;wordpress-serves-dynamic-pages&quot;&gt;WordPress Serves Dynamic Pages&lt;/h5&gt; &lt;p&gt;As WordPress pages are dynamic (i.e., built on the fly when someone visits your page and there is a fair amount of processing happening behind the scenes when you first load a page. Instead, use a caching plugin, which can increase the page’s loading speed by up to 5 times.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h5 id=&quot;the-most-popular-wordpress-cache-plugin&quot;&gt;The Most Popular WordPress Cache Plugin&lt;/h5&gt; &lt;p&gt;The most popular caching plugin for Wordpress that I found was &lt;em&gt;W3 Total Cache&lt;/em&gt;. It improves server performance by caching everything on your site and offers content delivery network integrations.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, that’s my list of reasons why WordPress page load speeds can take millions of years, I hope you’ve been able to learn something from my quick research efforts. If you would like to see me discuss anything else on this blog, please don’t hesitate to use the contact section on the home page to let me know. Thanks again for your time and feedback and as always, have a great day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Thanks to those of you who gave me feedback on my post, “Should I use WordPress or build my own website?”.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/loading_wait.jpg"/></entry><entry><title type="html">Fresh Website Theme</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/27/new_website_overhaul/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fresh Website Theme"/><published>2018-08-27T04:15:05+12:00</published><updated>2018-08-27T04:15:05+12:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/08/27/new_website_overhaul</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/27/new_website_overhaul/">&lt;p&gt;As you may have noticed, I’ve made some changes to the theme on this website.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in the previous post, I did this so you wouldn’t need to sign up to WordPress just to leave comments on the site. I’ve set up the contact page to send your messages directly to my email so we may communicate with each other more effectively. I hope that this will encourage you to give me feedback on things like my writing style and the kind of content you would like to see on this blog.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I elected to use a pre-made Jekyll theme as it saves me a lot of time, which is sparse while I’m still a student (poor in time and moneys…). If you like the look of it, you can check the theme out &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllthemes.org/themes/jekyll-material-theme/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Another reason I opted to move away from WordPress was because I found the WordPress theme took an absurdly long time to load. However, the plugins I had may have also contributed to the site loading slowly. The static Jekyll site has increased the overall performance of the website, which in turn will stop potential readers from giving up as they wait for the website to load.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I think this will be a temporary theme, as it still lacks some of the functionality I like to see on blogs, such as sections for ‘recent posts’ and ‘about me’. While I will add these pages in regardless of the theme, in the future, you will be seeing a lot of changes being made to this site. Eventually, I hope to make my own theme, which I may share (maybe on Wordpress of through Jekyll) if it turns out well.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Please let me know your thoughts on the new theme and what kind of content you’d like to see from me by using the contact page.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thanks for your time, as always, and have a good day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">As you may have noticed, I’ve made some changes to the theme on this website.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/website_redesign.jpg"/></entry><entry><title type="html">WordPress or build my own website?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/26/Should-I-use-WordPress-or-build-my-own-website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WordPress or build my own website?"/><published>2018-08-26T09:15:05+12:00</published><updated>2018-08-26T09:15:05+12:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/08/26/Should%20I%20use%20WordPress%20or%20build%20my%20own%20website</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/26/Should-I-use-WordPress-or-build-my-own-website/">&lt;p&gt;When building your own portfolio/website, should you use Wordpress for convenience or should you invest time in building it yourself?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hello everyone, I’m thinking about tearing down this WordPress site and creating my own website from scratch. The primary reason I’m considering this is because I don’t want you to have to sign up to Wordpress just to leave comments and communicate with me. At the moment, I’m pretty keen on building a simple Jekyll website for this blog, in addition to my own theme.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Please feel free to leave your opinions in the comments below or contact me directly. I’d really appreciate hearing your thoughts on whether I should create a new website or stick with what I’ve got here.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Have a good day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">When building your own portfolio/website, should you use Wordpress for convenience or should you invest time in building it yourself?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/wordpress_jekyll.jpg"/></entry><entry><title type="html">Building a website in an unknown framework</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/23/boss_ask_framework/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building a website in an unknown framework"/><published>2018-08-23T09:15:05+12:00</published><updated>2018-08-23T09:15:05+12:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/08/23/boss_ask_framework</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/23/boss_ask_framework/">&lt;p&gt;When building a website in a framework you don’t know, don’t be worried! I have some experience with this that I would like to share with you.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hello everyone, I hope you’re all well.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I’m still a bit fresh to web development, having only 6 months of part-time work experience with Logic Studio as I finish up my B.I.T. at the Otago Polytechnic. The main programming languages I use at work are: PHP, HTML, CSS, JS, and MySQL for databases&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;After re-familarising myself with these languages, I was assigned a new website (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.boys-trip.co.nz&quot;&gt;BoysTrip&lt;/a&gt;) to build in Silverstripe, a language with which I had no experience. With no time to crank out a textbook and do some light reading, I did what any good coder does: learn as you go. Of course, I ran into many problems but am lucky to work with a great team who are always eager to help me out. Never be scared to ask for help, whether from your classmates, your teachers, your co-workers, or people within the online community, like me!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;After much trial and error, I managed to understand Silverstripe enough to create something beautiful. While it took me far longer to create this site than a Senior Developer, it’s important to acknowledge where you stand; How much experience you have and what you can do with that to help your future work. If you put in the effort, you can learn a language and apply it to your work. After launching the website, our client gave me excellent feedback, &lt;em&gt;“Once again thanks for all your help with this, you’ve done an outstanding job”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;After finishing this website, we were asked to create a similar website by a business who were so impressed by it that they wanted their own, requesting me to build it! I was excited to continue using Silverstripe and to work with another professional client. With the previous website as my model, creating the second will only take a fraction of the time. I was able to copy+paste the backend code and make small touch-ups on the frontend.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Despite taking longer to create my first Silverstripe website, it was a valuable learning experience in the framework, handling clients and as a web developer in general.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading and remember, everything you don’t know is something you can learn to make yourself a better and more robust programmer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">When building a website in a framework you don’t know, don’t be worried! I have some experience with this that I would like to share with you.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/twoscreen.jpg"/></entry></feed>